Guide to the Stand Watie Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Stand Watie papers
1827-1977
1832-1870
WA MSS S-3204
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.21
(1 box)
Correspondence and legal, financial, land, and government records documenting Stand Watie's participation in the American Civil War and the government of the Cherokee Nation. Includes correspondence, land records, and a treaty draft documenting the use and negotiation of Creek and Cherokee land near Georgia and Oklahoma, 1827-1869; two receipts documenting the sale of enslaved African American people, 1832 and 1841; and letters among members of the Watie family, including Charles Watie, Charlotte Jacqueline Watie, John Watie, and Stand Watie, and their associates, including John Ross, concerning Watie family assets and family news, 1835-1937. Also includes three photographs of Watie family graves, 1976-1977.
Watie, Stand, 1806-1871
Scope and Contents
Correspondence and legal, financial, land, and government records documenting Stand Watie's participation in the American Civil War and the government of the Cherokee Nation. Includes correspondence, land records, and a treaty draft documenting the use and negotiation of Creek and Cherokee land near Georgia and Oklahoma, 1827-1869; two receipts documenting the sale of enslaved African American people, 1832 and 1841; and letters among members of the Watie family, including Charles Watie, Charlotte Jacqueline Watie, John Watie, and Stand Watie, and their associates, including John Ross, concerning Watie family assets and family news, 1835-1937. Also includes three photographs of Watie family graves, 1976-1977.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Stand Watie (1806-1871), Cherokee Nation leader; Confederate States brigadier general during the American Civil War; and brother of Elias Boudinot, also known as Buck Watie.
African Americans -- Cherokee Nation; Cherokee Indians -- Government relations; Cherokee Indians -- Politics and government -- 19th century; Cherokee Indians -- Treaties; Indians of North America; Slavery -- Cherokee Nation; Slave trade -- United States; Cherokee Nation; Photographs; Legal documents -- Cherokee Nation -- 19th century; William Reese Co.; Ross, John, 1790-1866; Watie, Charles; Watie, Charlotte Jacqueline, 1854-1875; Watie, John, active 1835-1937; Watie, Stand, 1806-1871
- Land grant to William N. Brimer, signed by George M. Troup, granting 202.5 acres of Creek land, 1827-06-18 (Box 1)
- Land grant to Joseph E. Akridge, signed by Wilson Lumpkin, granting forty acres of Cherokee land, 1832-12-12 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  The document signs over forty acres of land currently occupied by the Cherokee Indians in accordance of a Georgia State Act titled "an Act to lay out the Gold Region in the Lands, at present in the occupancy of the Cherokee Indians, into small lots, and dispose of the same by separate Lottery." Also includes a small plot map a wax seal of the State of Georgia.
- Surveyor's plat document, completed in manuscript, granting 160 acres of Cherokee land to George Perdee, 1832 (Box 1)
- Slave sale receipts, 1832, 1841 (Box 1)
  The first receipt is for $12 dollars for payment made by Elias Boudinot "in part payment for the hire of a negro man for one year commencing March 1, 1832." The second receipt is for $750 for full payment "for a negro man named Andy" issued to Andrew M. Varn.
- Letter from General William Lambert to Thomas Green, 1833-01-17 (Box 1)
  Addresses Congress' response to the Cherokee appeals to Georgia's land claims.
- Letter from Harriet Boudinot to Stand Watie, approximately 1835 (Box 1)
  A letter addressed to Stand Watie at New Echota, Cherokee Nation, Georgia, sending family news and greetings as well as expressing her views about current negotiations with the state of Georgia.
- Note from John Ross to Joshua Barker, 1836-04-08 (Box 1)
- Promissory notes, 1836- (Box 1)
  Promissory notes issued to Caganattuga and Daylight, signed.
- Circular containing a letter from Joel Roberts Poinsett, Secretary of War, concerning the New Echota Treaty and the location of Cherokee Indians east of the Mississippi, 1838 (Box 1)
- John Ridge estate documents, 1839- (Box 1)
  Two documents listing debts owed to the estate of John Ridge.
- Letter from Robert Armstrong to Stand Watie, 1846-05-22 (Box 1)
  Letter discusses the strife among the Cherokee people and relates news of a meetings of the Ross party and others.
- John Watie financial document, 1846-08-24 (Box 1)
  Pay order for $96.25 paid out of the "public money received by the Treaty Party" for "the clothing and other articles received for the use of the men under my command."
- William Cordry property loss claim, 1846 (Box 1)
  Claim filed against the United States for the loss of house, land, and property "abandoned in the year 1845" in the amount of $141.62. Sworn before and signed by John Thompson Adair as judge in the Superior Court of the Cherokee Nation.
- Treaty agreement draft, approximately 1846 (Box 1)
  Manuscript draft in an unidentified hand of an agreement to restore peace and equanimity among the Cherokee people. Possibly a working draft of the agreement created in order to bind the Old Settlers and the Treaty Party (including Watie) to the Cherokee Treaty of 1846.
- Financial memorandum for members of Watie's faction, approximately 1846 (Box 1)
  Itemized list of damages sustained from the Ross party, totaling $1620 and including theft of cash, horses, hogs, and other goods.
- Letter to Stand Watie, 1847-08-11 (Box 1)
  A letter of transmittal for a letter to be sent on to the President and asking for Watie's opinion about its contents and other matters regarding the Council.
- J.W. Washbourne receipt for John Ridge, 1848-07-31 (Box 1)
  Document acknowledging receipt of a payment on behalf of John Ridge's widow.
- Horse Fly Estate payment, 1848 (Box 1)
  Payment for Horse Fly Estate, in the amount of $20.50, with Stand Watie as executor.
- Stand Watie property sale document, 1850-01-01 (Box 1)
  Listing of goods "For Sale cheap for cash" including millstones, bolting cloth, and assorted sundries.
- Certification of Stand Watie as a member of the National Council of the Cherokee Nation, 1853-08-02 (Box 1)
  Certification signed by the superintendents and clerks of the Delaware District of the Cherokee Nation that Stand Watie has been elected as a member of the National Council.
- P. Woodward letter to Stand Watie, 1850-02-13 (Box 1)
  Letter notifying Watie that Woodward has turned over $40 received from John P. Dodd.
- Letter from Charles Watie to his brother, 1855-03-13 (Box 1)
  Letter relating that there is no work in the mines and that he believes that his son, Jack, is dead.
- Letter from Cornelius to an unidentified recipient, 1860-05-29 (Box 1)
- Regulations for payment to deceased Confederate Army members, 1862-1864 (Box 1)
  Also includes correspondence stating that the regulations are not intended to apply to the claimants of the several Indian Nations.
- Orders addressed to Stand Watie, 1865-04-13 (Box 1)
  Manuscript orders addressed to Stand Watie as Brigadier General of the Cherokee Cavalry.
- Stand Watie shipment receipt, 1869-02-24 (Box 1)
  Printed receipt, completed in manuscript, for goods shipped by Watie to Ford Gibson, Oklahoma aboard the Steamboat Fort Smith.
- James Bell receipt from the Cherokee Nation Treasury Department, 1869-08-24 (Box 1)
  Receipt for the purchase of two lots in Fort Gibson, Oklahoma.
- Letter from D.P. Bell to Jacqueline Watie, 1870-02-16 (Box 1)
- James M. Bell legal licenses, 1870, 1879 (Box 1)
  Two manuscript documents indicating Bell's license to practice law in the Cherokee Nation.
- Letters to Jacqueline Watie from Arizona Bunch, 1874- (Box 1)
  Includes notes on ideas of marriage and the desirability of marrying an Indian. Also reminisces about their years at Clarke's Academy in Webbers Falls, Arkansas.
- Family letters, event invitations, and photographs of graves, 1881-1977 (Box 1)
- James Bell land allotments, 1905-1906 (Box 1)
  Two certificates of allotment for land purchased by Bell, Cherokee Nation.
- Letter from Gaston L. Litton to Mrs. O.A. Cox regarding Watie family, 1937-04-21 (Box 1)
- John M. Watie lost cattle claim, undated (Box 1)
  Claim for cattle lost on a drive.